Hello there!
Warm welcome to Lund University and debate in Lund,
The forum where some of the university's sharpest brains get the chance to
Freight off with you and with carefully selected and invited guests.
This is a television program in which we do not hesitate to make visibly simple things even more complicated.
We do this because this is a university, we are not afraid of it.
We want to turn around and turn things, preferably with you and we do
According to the principles that debate in Lund has been established for over ten years now.
We have debated exactly everything you can think of under heaven and earth
but we try to do it in a way that leaves you with new questions
And not just ready -made answers.
To succeed, you need to have a fantastic panel that you should just get to meet.
My name is Andreas Ekström,
Is a program manager today and is available everyday at Sydsvenskan's editorial staff.
We turn to the stage!
We have a debate that will be about meritocracy today.
And to take on what we first Martin Wolgast, a psychologist and researcher.
Welcome Martin!
Thanks so much.
Nina Björk has been able to hike up to the Academic Association today because you are Lundabo.
Warm welcome!
While the author and columnist Lena Andersson has been allowed to travel anyway from Stockholm,
We thank you for that.
Welcome here.
Last but not least we also meet Max Benner
which is the principal of the School of Economics at Lund University.
Hello Mats, welcome.
Since we are going to discuss such an interesting topic as meritocracy, I think we believe
must start by defining the question itself, all panelists should do so,
What we mean by meritocracy.
The best thing, however, is that we have to find out
a part about discrimination in working life
And how social inequality is recreated.
Among other things in a report that we released last fall
Where, among other things, we discuss meritocracy and ideologies about eritocracy
And their role in recreating inequalities.
It sounds extremely merit I think.
Nina Björk.
You came out with a book last year that I suspect may have to do with your merit
for this evening but you have to decide for yourself how you want
Present yourself on this issue.
Yeah i'd probably think that is
And not just that I could go here.
I wrote this one
"If one loves freedom" and the first chapter in it is called
"When does the competition for meritocracy start?".
So that's probably why someone thought of me.
I think so, too, I who have some insight into the process has gone.
Lena Andersson, you have written
about many things, many carrying
Cutting points you have moved to in the public debate for many years in Dagens Nyheter,
Now Svenska Dagbladet.
What can it be that makes meritocracy a question for you?
Yes, but an important point here is that it is the editorial staff that knows the answer to that question.
So there is someone who chooses who should sit here.
I haven't chosen it myself.
And then I was apostropized in a
Underline in Swedish last winter, I don't know if it matters.
As you answered later.
Any philosopher who wrote about this,
We were both wrong, I think he thought.
You should have room to prove the opposite here now just right, of course few
Rub yourself against the views as well.
Mats Benner, who leads the School of Economics, which is the Faculty of Economic at this university.
What places you on this chair?
I lost a bet.
I do not know.
I am also wrong, maybe
and have been interested in me litigant for the question of
Knowledge is power or whether power is knowledge.
You have a solid background in researching research, if you express it, so,
Tell us a little about it, what are you looking at there?
The research is absolutely absolute.
It's all about, maybe not the truth, but approach it.
At the same time it is a social process,
it is about
Groups, constellations and other things and how those two things are interconnected.
One raw meritocratic and the other raw social.
Would you be able to say, I do not know.
No, but I thought that sounded very interesting.
I think we can find a little different
Both common views and disparate views in this gang.
If we start by saying that you may say each thing that
motivates why a metro -crocatic system has its points.
You do not have to fully decide that you are connecting to all forms of,
You do not have to be so drastic or complete in this answer but we start some end.
What are the obvious benefits of having a system based on we
formally merit us for assignments?
It would be a partial component in such cases in what is usually mean by meritocracy.
It would be to have some kind of prejudicial recruitment
Or some kind of prejudice -free selection process.
Can you?
No.
Okay, you'll have to immerse just here.
Nina, what can be good about looking at the formal merits?
Yes.
That we don't think "yes, but I know her or him",
I can pay to get this place or punch in any context.
About the same thing as ...
What does Lena say?
As defended the system perhaps the clearest of all of us here.
Thus, this with meritocracy is a conceptual confusion as with many concepts but
It is an organizational principle for how to appoint
Positions where demand is greater than the supply.
Any principle must be had for how to go about
And this is a principle.
It replaced historically then that
The aristocracy received the items that they considered was best.
But it was also a kind of meritocracy because then they thought they were the best.
there the meritocracy is the only one almost as one recognizes openly
is what determines who gets a job.
That's how it is.
No, it's good for talking to Churchills
Definition of democracy: The worst system we have minus everyone else.
So that it is extremely incorrect and hollow and other but what is the alternative?
Yes, about what Lena said, burden.
But it is fun because now you take us into the next step that you are curious about.
Give up what is bad then give you what we lose.
What is not good about this way?
If you start in your world, the university world.
But it is probably the illusion that it is complete,
Without it, it is like all systems that it is important to
Carpentry and hammer based on its imperfections.
If you look at the meritocracy, after all
This panel had looked different 40 years ago.
I don't think anyone with the experiences we have been sitting in such a panel then.
Why not?
Because there were other norms and conceptions of what was interesting
Positions and attitudes then.
In your world it is so that you can appeal, you are looking for a job,
a lecturer, one is looking for a professorship
and so you don't get it
Since someone else has been considered in overall assessment more suitable, thus has better qualifications,
Then you have an opportunity in the university world to appeal this decision
And so do many.
Everything former but it occurs.
But then at least I react as a layman on the basis that
I do not want to hire someone who not only accepts that he or she is not selected in that situation,
Keep on and appeal, I don't want an accident into the gang.
It is a merit for me that the relevant appeals,
It is directly a cultural influence of the culture that exists in appeal.
What does it look like at the university?
It is fine, that you can question.
It is
positive with meritocracy, that you can have a discussion about which qualifications are valida
And how it has been assessed.
Because that's what the appeal is about.
Of course there is after all
Emotional overtones in appeals but they are still a kind
Opportunity to question notions of what is good and right.
May I say I have,
My entrance to the meritocracy is to
it is the way of our time to
Legitimize an unequal society and just as you said, historically it would not be we who sat here.
But before, one could legitimize inequality in a society by the fact that
Say that some people were actually more worthy than others, by burden.
Men stand over women, the white race superior other breeds.
Then one could refer to God's will or nature, it is founded,
It is natural, biologically determined.
Then it also becomes natural to take an unequal society if people are very worthy,
Then society should be a pyramid and a hierarchy.
But today we think that all people are equally worthy,
No one is automatically born to a superior position.
Then you might think you don't want one,
But many people think that it is important with inequality and that we
shall continue to live in an unequal society.
How do you do it when you then assume that everyone is equally worthy?
Then I mean that one uses the meritocracy as a legitimation for the new inequality,
to defend inequality.
To maintain an unequal system.
Yes and that the meritocracy is nevertheless
founded in things that one does not recognize.
The defenders of meritocracy say it will be about
the individual's own achievements, own merits,
own choices, own efforts
so that an individual should not be placed
somewhere because of skin color or sex.
I have a feeling that you could get fire support from Martin Wolgast at that point.
No, because it's not about being, or of course, that's for sure,
that you discriminate, you have prejudice and therefore do not see the same merit as the same
Depending on who has done it, so to speak.
But I mean the meritocracy could not disregard inheritance
Because we are not born the same,
We are not genetically the same
and some people have a greater apt to learn the things that just our time reward,
Just as some people were stronger and snabbers when it was important,
so some have an innate
Easy to learn merit paths through school and understand what the school is all about.
Or a congenital skin color that can come on well maybe.
What do you say about it Martin?
I think it's important to keep some things apart here.
I mean that meritocracy is something more than what Lena defined it as,
a way to add individual services.
We have other concepts for that,
we could call it for
that we try to recruit on skills or something similar.
Meritocracy for me is, if one is to understand it in a larger context, is a way to distribute,
Based on what principles we want status, resources and power
Should be distributed in our society in a broader way.
And then, just like Nina, I think that then meritocracy says that it should
is based on some kind of principle as we
legitimate based on the fact that one has earned the position you have,
based on efforts and talent or something similar.
I think that is a very difficult position to defend
When we see what society looks like.
I mean that meritocracy
is problematic for that number one:
does not work in practice.
We are born to overly unequal conditions both socially and
Genetic factors that Nina highlighted.
I also mean that it is worrying to try to strive for increased meritocracy
in that way because
What we risk getting into is that when we do
So we reinforce the place these differences.
It will be this legitimation and maintenance of the hierarchies instead.
We see that quite clearly in research that the greater, the greater
The greater extent one encompasses meritocratic principles, the more negative one is to measures such as
would benefit disadvantaged groups and equalize differences in society.
But how else should you get up then,
If one does not have these conditions, if you do not have these
genetic or these good parents.
So you should still get out without contacts, without your social habituation, how to do it?
Then the meritocracy is your only rescue?
It is to place the most suitable person in the right place.
Fine, fine.
It is possible but the National Encyclopedia,
Should I quote “Meritocracy Definition:
Social order in which individuals are ranked
and social rewards, income status, distributed according to ability and merits, often valued
after the training fair's qualifications. ”
So it is not only a suitable person in the appropriate place but it is also that the person
should be able to get
other rewards than to
be in a place there
It hopefully comes into its own.
Without different rewards it would be easier to
realize the freedom of the individual,
To do what it actually has to do.
For now if you choose certain roads,
If you have the opportunity to choose certain roads, then you get so much.
One gets money,
You get status, you also get longer life,
Several years with health.
There is a great moral merit in this but do you have any value for someone else
Is not obvious.
The system we have
is based on that
people are chosen to things, if you look for things you want to do
and so we are in a market where there is free competition and so you pay people for it
they do and so corresponds to that
what someone wants, corresponds like someone who wants to do it and so
occurs an exchange of money.
And everything that comes with this.
So I think it is mixed up with this that you
“I think it's right
That anyone who has money should have it better ”.
Can you break in here?
According to the debate rules, you just have to throw in so I do.
Looking at the history behind the concept
Meritocracy, after all, was a criticism of an ourritocracy meritocracy.
The name when determined that there were certain proportions
that were study -motivated or not study -motivated,
It was really a criticism
against not introducing it as in Sweden to compulsory school in the UK.
The argument was that one third is needed that is
Manual Labor, one third is needed who are officials and need a third as
Consumers for happy life, roughly.
So you could say it was
a kind of reconciliation around that
The talent is like static.
The whole idea of our elementary school that is some kind of meritocratic meritocracy,
at least as a idea of origin,
It was that
There is a so -called talent reserve.
So there are experiences, roles and positions that are not recognized by today's system,
It is important to avoid being filtered away
in the name of a static division of places and positions.
We all feel close to the hope that there are meritocratic features in meritocracy, much like
democracy,
Someone said jokingly that one quit
say the truth of the Riksdag after the right to vote became general,
Because then you could no longer say as it was.
And of course it was a huge meaning,
places and positions and experiences.
Then it was no longer the elites,
This was then said out of a
Not a meritocratic perspective, that it was better than when they were fixed positions.
An ideal way with a meritocratic system understands its own limitations.
She says there is now something we miss here, there is talent or
competence or something else.
There is a very famous example of that.
I think it was the Symphony Orchestra in Toronto that was first with this,
That when you hire musicians, you simply start letting them play behind a screen,
they may go in without shoes so one could not imagine if it was a man or a woman who stepped in
to the instrument and then they got to play.
Then they recruited much more women than you did before.
But what we have to hold on is if we talk about the principle or how it is implemented,
implemented in reality.
It is still all the time in all examples we arrive at
That you should try to take the most appropriate.
It is very difficult to get around.
Yes, but the meritocracy consists of two parts and
I agree that you can call it something else.
The suitability section is part and the reward part is another part.
Then it is also as you say you can have a point of view
that the most deserving will come at the top
or so one might have the point of view that
"Yes, it doesn't have to be deserving, it was lucky perhaps he found something
As many with money want '
And then it comes at the top.
Yes, it gets money and it gets power.
If you buy other people's labor, you get power after all
And it gets status and so on.
I don't like that system either.
The problem with the meritocracy that one describes an unequal society as it is fair,
Like it could be fair.
Even if you do not know if it is a woman or man and then you hire more women means that,
the defenders of meritocracy would also say that it is not good
Because there should be no discrimination.
But I mean it can never build on
Something other than inherited factors and then there is nothing that separates the meritocracy ...
Then there is nothing that legitimizes our inequality
It does not choose this.
But when you say this legitimizes an unequal system,
so do you base it on the idea that man's
Natural conditions are equality, Rousseau.
And then we are destroyed by society.
I don't know if it is natural or unnatural but it is something we can strive ...
The word legitimize, it sounds like someone is insidious.
I think it's insidious because no one is saying
"We want an unequal system based on unfair things like birth".
Yes, it does if you ...
You might do it.
Yes I do.
Then I think it is honorable of you.
I do this because freedom leads to inequality,
So if people are allowed to be free and shape their lives, it will not be the same life.
No.
And then we can say that we have a society that can make these different lives
Really can be different.
You like to do it, I like to do it but no one should have to die earlier than anyone else.
But there will be different status, we will never come from different status for people will value
this.
What you have done is to see through the social liberals.
Because they feel so bad that their freedom leads to inequality.
That is what you have seen in your texts.
I think that is good that they feel bad but I think they should know that they are feeling bad.
But you ignore it, that it will be, you are not social liberal ...
If I get to break in then I think
That it is very interesting to discuss ideas on a principle level
but the risk is that we somehow forget
the social reality that the ideas are in
And in what social function in some way.
There I think there is a great contrast to meritocracy,
Parts of what was meritocracy anyway, this is not being able to inherit positions through burden.
Yes, it was radically once in a while,
Today it is not very radical.
Today I mean that an ideology
who say that, which I think meritocracy is, so it is used socially, politically,
In the political conversation,
who say that successes in society are determined by
one's performance in one way or another, that's the society we have, in some way.
It is a system, it is an ideology that
Defends and recreates the differences.
I also think you see it clearly empirically.
In recent decades, we see a trend towards increased inequality, increased segregation.
In research you can see that it also leads to that,
In a society that is segregated you get less
insight into the living conditions of others
And the unequal conditions that can shape people.
Which in turn leads to the fact that you think "I have made a lot of effort for what I have achieved",
Because you compare with others who have had the same conditions I have had.
These are the ones I can compare myself to
And then you see that I have plugged really hard, I have struggled and I have one and the other.
And then you get an increased confidence that the profits I have made, what I have achieved,
I have done this because of my own efforts,
one encompasses to a greater extent
meritocratic ideal or that one thinks that is what is to rule
And that society also a ruling on meritocratic factors.
Which in turn leads to the fact that one thinks that when it comes to political suggestions
which is about equalizing differences in
Living conditions and conditions so do you think "why should we do it? I have fought for this"
And then you have a closed circle back to continued increased inequality.
In this way I mean that it is interconnected and then you can
discuss based on the kind of principle idea world,
it already made Plato who meant that we should have a meritocratic
It is not unthinkable that the one who has it
The biggest expertise will also be the best to decide the most.
Can you imagine Nina, a system where you keep the hierarchy in that,
It is inevitable with a certain social status, we have war right now, you can then be a trauma surgeon in Ukraine
So follows a status of it but you do not receive a higher salary than the one who does other tasks.
Can one imagine separating,
Status you can never do anything about in any society but you can do anything about economics.
Can you imagine, what keeps a meritocracy that only rewards status but not money?
Yes, I want us to have equal pay for different work.
And that's exactly it.
But that does not mean that I think we should draw about who should ...
But then it will be that some will be managers, some will have
It is clear that some will have more fun jobs.
But when you give one everything,
thus one gives both money, status, longevity
And own power over everyday life and everything.
Then it becomes like such a direction.
But I think you can compensate.
If we are going to go into cultural things as well.
I'll tell you a little story about Mats Benner sitting away on one edge.
About 1.5-2 years ago, Lund University would appoint a new principal.
It goes in a very special way that you know.
It is based on people nominating the colleagues they think could be appropriate.
Then it is an advanced process with many steps.
Then I think Mats Benner was genuinely shocked to find himself on the so -called short list,
with a small few candidates left.
When Mats was interviewed in Sydsvenskan and so he could only with difficulty as well as deal with
That he was so moved and like it was very shocking.
I wonder if it wasn't extremely merit, Mats, that you genuinely
Be so surprised that so many people think you were a good principal candidate.
And now you are the principal at the School of Economics as well.
It makes me think
What Peter Englund in the Swedish Academy once said when I interviewed him and asked him
"How do people do, they tell you that they want to join the Swedish Academy or not?"
And then he said with some cold:
"The rise is not a merit".
These are strong words.
I want to hear a little about the university culture, that's why I took this story.
Can't you imagine that there is a kind of triangulation here?
Meritocracy and market have a little
driving force or ambitions we have.
Thus the meritocracy that we want
Read or write or we want to mark ourselves in one way or another.
The market is still a kind, yes.
It has turned out that there is a certain person ...
There is some connection between reward and effort.
But when meritocracy and market are roughly mixed, I can only mention as for example, on,
And it is a guessing competition to the moderator, what percentage of the grades at Princeton University
Is A, so the highest rating?
Certainly much more than we think, I would like to be 40, 50%.
70%.
And counting.
Because there you pay there to get a tip rating.
Because it costs $ 60,000 a year and read there so there is a strong
Power and Åtundan.
It is a corrupt system, after all, we must say that.
It is clear that they live in a certain critical balance those two.
What I would like to add the third, now I do not say that I am devoting myself to it,
But you could call that care.
But when appointing university rector and pope
Can't show that you are interested.
It is culturally interesting anyway.
But it is very difficult to know what that task really is.
The one sitting and
imagine what it means to lead
In any business I would say but not least
A creative and somewhat unpredictable business, universities are wrong with it.
Without it, it is important to be within some kind of balance between
The one I myself am the organism that I am a part of.
I think it's the three really,
So pure meritocracy
need some kind of relationship with the market
Insight that there is something suspicious that you want power.
There is something suspicious about it.
One should not want to control over others,
You should go there reluctantly.
Do the panel think it is a good principle, overall?
Yes, too much yster in enthusiasm is always a bit strange.
Whatever the matter?
Well, I don't think so.
If we go back, that is, too,
Present positions always the lectures of others.
You have to be able to go back.
For it is the reverse meritocracy that one can accept another position
If you now think it is on loan.
But what is justice then?
Yes, but the mathematically objectively best suited person is not there
for particularly many assignments after all or for different types of status regulation without it is about someone
Vag cocktail with different ingredients when we finally decide what is fair or merit.
Can we bare a little in what we mean by justice?
Does Lena want to start?
No, it's too hard.
I think that too, that's why I ask you.
The whole state is about justice or
righteousness as the Swedish translation is
And they do not come up with what it is so it is a very difficult concept.
You could say that justice is that the person who is deserving of something should get it, you can say is justice.
And then what it is to be deserved is another issue.
But in any case it is very natural to us I would like to say that
Know when someone is very undeserved.
So do we think why should it do that?
So we seem to have any feeling of legal?
However, for example, when the hosts get a Caribbean sail that was
So it became a scream even though it would then be positive for their rehabilitation
and return to a non-criminal life
So maybe you think they would have to go to
The North Pole or something that is
Hard, not so nice, not enviable.
Here you can say that you have made an effort by not becoming a criminal, it is a kind of effort.
For some anyway.
No, but for everyone.
You still have to decide to follow the law and take care of yourself.
So it's not just that, now I disappear here.
Yes, you do a little neighbor.
I think you should think that justice and injustice are not in nature, it is as it is.
Some are born with some abilities, you can't say that is unfair.
It is not unfair that someone
Is good that way so that it is rewarded in our society.
However, when that,
But when it's so
because of this as just
existed that people have not decided so people can either decide to
Yes, we shall reinforce this or we should not reinforce the advantage anyone can have through their birth
or the disadvantage of being born
handicapped or something.
There, man comes in and there you can create justice or injustice.
For justice and injustice
Is always a human issue, always a social and cultural question not a natural issue.
But you have also used the concept of "the competing man" at some point when we have talked
Before this.
A meritocracy also means that we stand side by side on a starting line
And then we will get to some kind of goal.
Anyone who comes first comes in different ways to be privileged.
How does it take
The contemporary man to live in this constant competition?
Is it that it must be so all the way from
That we were monkeys or is it a chosen system?
So I don't think there's a
necessity in that communities are based on competition that people's
Natural relationship when you meet another person is to compete with her.
I do not think so.
In our society it is, after all,
We live in a competitive society and it starts ...
That's what you talk about social liberals.
They have a little trouble taking the competition to start when
You start the six -year business, that's when you start qualifying and competing for the grades
And so on, it turns out,
They do not arrive at the starting line at the same time.
We must compensate for that.
Then we have to remove the children from the parents so that the competition can be fair.
Not many people want to.
Then it is also the case that if we say we should have a competition
Then we also say that we have to behave in the same way
To win, to achieve success because one cannot have a competition there
Each and every other goes on their own desire.
Have you arranged a competition in running and someone feels they want to jump instead of running,
Now the races start and then it starts to jump, it will not win that competition.
All competitions make us uniform,
They force us to behave in the same way, strive for the same things.
It is interesting Martin, after all,
Then I have to ask you as a scientist, you look around among your colleagues,
You read international literature in the same research field as you.
How homogeneous and heterogeneous manage the university to be
When you still observe these methods?
After all, you live in the same psychological and social reality as everyone else.
It is very homogeneous and that is what I mean we need to see,
very objective ways to measure
Merit and then we still know that,
from research for example,
An equivalent performance with is judged differently depending on who it is that makes it,
It has been seen in so -called
expert assessments that
a man with a certain level of merit, certain amount of publication and so on
is considered more qualified than a woman with the equivalent.
And we also see a bias for example in
the connection between how merit you are and what return you get on the merits that also
goes in line with those
so it looks like a higher merit level is required
For women to get the same, to be judged as as competent as a man.
It's interesting, you also lifted this "what can you do then?"
and is not then that at least
The bad system that Mats was in.
I think an interesting factor to discuss there is this with quotation
Because it puts things at their tip a bit.
If we were to use any other principle, what would it look like?
Or supplementary principles are often.
One merit 85 or 90 % of students
Then you create a small quota for a small part of it.
And then I thought, it was done a rather interesting study, then it was in itself
a political science study that looked at the effect of what happened to competence
before and after starting to apply quotation
And then it was seen that competence increased after they began to use quotas
when adding these assignments.
The reason for it increased it was not that they
women who were recruited what more competent
Without the men
Social reality.
Is it enough as a definition to identify?
Yes, then we'll see, okay so which ...
Then we must be able to talk about issues both in workplaces and in society at large
where we also dare talk about inequalities based
On social perceptions of race, so to speak.
One thing you have to remember is actually the one who chooses a person.
We have a system where you are not only assigned a place, the one who also
are free to choose the one they want for their
workplace or to one's
training or whatever it is to be chosen.
If it is as you say then there are discrimination factors
That makes not everyone has the same chance ...
It is the selection itself that is discrimination, one always discriminates against
When choosing someone over someone else,
It is always a discrimination.
It is an exclusion you can say but it does not have to be discrimination,
If we now like meritocracy,
So it is not one,
So it doesn't have to be a discrimination if the most qualified gets it.
However, if the person who gets it comes from one
Social group that does not usually get it then it is after all
One way to think, yes otherwise it would have been discrimination.
I think we must also hear, because we started with the question of what benefits there are
With the system, probably must start with hearing a little more from the away flank,
Are there times when meritocracy is inappropriate?
So I don't think you should be so afraid of imperfection,
What we talk about is, after all, as well as ways of discovering ...
I mean for me, meritocracy will always go before bureaucracy,
So you point out in the opposition for it becomes,
at least in the contexts that deal with that
create or develop, it is another matter if there is a pure management because then you can
Define the roles over time.
One should not be afraid of,
Yes but as I said, no one speaks Scanian in this panel,
It looks a bit anyway, at least me.
It is still possible to implement this in Lund during
Lund University's banner.
So it is clear that it happens as well as shifts.
It's fun that you say it because it would be absurd if we thought in advance:
"None of these speak Scanian, it is not possible, we have to quote in a scan speaker."
There has been a meritocratic adaptation of the debate format, we need not be
plain.
We don't have to be
Super homogeneous without we can ...
There is some kind of, after all,
Yes but it is extremely imperfect but there are many examples of this, search processes are crazy.
I mean, if you look at highly meritocratic
systems like American universities so they had for a long time
so -called Jewish quota,
For one would not have too much Jewish students and too much Jewish teachers
Because there was too little party and too much studies.
So you had a quota, not to take in but to exclude?
Paul Samuelson who received the economy award ended up at MIT instead of Harvard for
The Juda rat was filled.
When are we talking now?
Late 40s, after the war.
It is in the same vein, so also Lund University has a fair
Shameful history when it comes to receiving Jewish students.
One should not be so scared of imperfections for
We discover time, after another,
imperfections in the meritocracy and work them in.
No, I mean it's not an imperfection just like that either.
In a pluralistic society there are a lot of things, if debate in Lund was
That you should be a scan, then you have decided to recruit.
There is nothing wrong with, for example, in association there,
I saw something in Sweden around, there was an association for
People named Kenneth,
I do not feel discriminated against not being allowed to be there.
Fantastic discrimination case, it is wonderful.
If a criterion for being here is to be scan
And maybe have someone to knowledge
Then it is so and you have to ask if there are other debates you can join.
But these are factors that do not relate to something important in our society that it looks like today.
However, the example that Mats lifted with American elite university is that
decisive for whether one of them has been passed on, it is a shortcut to extremely well -paid positions
And a lot of status and power in society.
And there, for example, it is, you called it extremely meritocratic institutions,
And there it is so that
The top percent
has an equal proportion of the places there, ie in terms of income and wealth,
Has the same proportion of the places there as the lower 50%.
And then we may think it is meritocratic.
Then I mean it's meritocratic
Because it is so meritocracy is used.
One could also see it as it is not meritocratic for meritocracy
should be an abstract
Idea that we could formulate in some philosophical way.
But it is a philosophical idea and nothing else.
I know it but you have to see how it is used, what it has for social function.
You have to talk about what you should have instead.
An equal education system compensatory,
that tries to bridge differences and which are inclusive.
Then will some stand back then?
Children of academics may not go to university.
That's not what I say, I say like this:
that the problem of quotation and that type of efforts or that you have reserves places,
It is that they come very late in an event, to try to intervene
very late in a event
Which creates a certain outcome.
The earlier we can intervene, the better it is.
So it is important to try to build an education system from the beginning
which is compensatory
For example, and that provide more opportunities
to inclusion.
Then it may mean that you do not treat everyone exactly the same.
Then we need to bet more money in schools
They can apparently.
Yes, but you think it's wrong?
I don't know if I should legislate against it.
I do not think so.
I think it's a stupid idea for a university because it's about knowledge.
However, I think those who hire them then should see how they have come there.
But may they do it?
So, just because you have money you don't have to be stupid.
No and it may not be that difficult to do it either.
The university's idea is knowledge
And not to buy a place.
It should be few.
Then you think we have made great progress during the pandemic with what one calls
Massive online courses, mox, with a ugly expression.
Then such universities could graduate incredibly many people who can be proud of
to have gone on Harvard or Princeton
Or brown but you don't.
It is because one wants to maintain the economic value in this, of course,
hardly the merit value, without it must be a funding thing
Which makes you choose to do so, I guess.
Yes.
Philosopher Jonna Bornemark wrote a book called "The Unfortunate Renaissance"
Which was embraced by many.
How do you relate to it as a leader?
I ask you Mats if you have
Responsibility as a managerial assignment.
Next question.
It is difficult.
Incredibly difficult.
What I get for, as you probably understand is when the variable makes the system
imperfect and how to relate to it.
It is the core that I am looking for.
If you are going to defend the meritocracy, you think it is the best we have,
How do you do it to stand it up if you do not want to quote for example, then there are other ways.
You talked about imperfection before.
How do you do to
Understand this so that it still manages as the least bad system we have.
But that is precisely this kind of
Interventions and discussions about what we do.
But that is for taking
What is there to pick up there, where is there, how can we give back to that environment?
What I myself at least try
think, I try to live by Groucho Marx's old Maxim that I never join the associations such as
Accepts me as a member.
Then we have this with the Åtundan again.
So one should question contexts that feel very homogeneous.
Very much of what undermines meritocracy it is when it goes into homogeneity
When it's at it's best
So it has a look for the unique and the special and the remarkable.
As we approach the hour full here I will
Ask you, we have many students here in the audience and certainly many via television too,
If you come to Lund University or any other university and will qualify.
You come as 19, 20, 21-year-old, you choose courses and programs and
So one should drive forward towards becoming an adult,
prevail in a broad sense.
So we now have meritocracy, we also have lots of people who say you should build your network,
Engage yourself socially and get many friends that you can benefit from.
If you were to give an advice
to the student who will be new to Lund this fall and will take on all that there is
in a life as a university student.
To balance then
Contact network construction with this merit, plug against the exam versus to spend time with ...
What is an approach?
Do you want to give good advice?
Maybe you can start Martin.
Yes, I would say that one should try to take advantage of the time you have received
And try to have fun.
The merit can be solved later.
Nina?
It depends on what you want to achieve but if you want a job then you should well
Find out what the companies think it is possible to make profits in
The future and so are invested in training in that area.
Throughout for
People who have gone well in the world I have noticed it is that they have taken the wrong door.
They came late to an enrollment or they happened to go to a house other than they thought and then
did they do their best
In the house they entered.
Was a little curious, was a little bold.
It is interesting because now you say that the choice does not play a huge role, but it is like the effort later.
A bit like Lena, do what you do properly.
Yes.
Isn't it a wonderful summary word for your discussion about meritocracy.
We can measure in different ways but do what you do properly.
I think we thank the panel with these wise words.
You have met
Martin Wolgast, Nina Björk, Lena Andersson and Mats Benner
And you have looked at debate in Lund from Lund, the Academic Association.
A few times a year we show up in a box near you.
Thank you for watching, thank you for coming here.